35, ל''ה, Lamed Hey, but we pick up at the very bottom
of ל''ד עמוד ב', Lamed Dalet Amud Bet, we just have a
few lines left to wrap up the previous discussion. And so just
to remind us what we were up to, the גמרא Gemara had
been going, had a statement, I won't even say now how we
got to the original statement of רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan that if
you have טמא tamei grapes, you can extract the grape juice, the
wine, in a way that doesn't make it טמא tamei by doing
less than a כביצה kebeitzah at any time, and therefore there won't,
when the juice actually comes out, there won't be enough of the
grapes to transfer the טומאה tumah to the juice. So we had
a whole דף daf yesterday which was leading up to, had another
discussion which was ultimately leading up to bringing that line in. And
the other discussion was a משנה Mishna that taught that if you
have טמא תרומה, tamei Trumah, you can plant it and the טומאה
tumah goes away, but the תרומה Trumah remains problematic. And the question
is like, make up your mind, if the טומאה tumah goes away,
why does the תרומה Trumah remain problematic? And the גמרא Gemara had
a few answers, but finally the answer the גמרא Gemara said was
based on a teaching of ריש לקיש Resh Lakish or this statement
that in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael they knew this and in בבל
Bavel they didn't know this, which was that we have different standards
for things that are holy and things that are not holy. Things
that are not holy, there's this principle called זריעה, zreia, you plant
it in the ground and the טומאה tumah goes away, or if
you have water, you immerse it in the מקוה, mikveh, it's like
you're planting it in the מקוה mikveh almost, is the same word
used, and the טומאה tumah goes away. But if the thing was
holy and became טמא, tamei, then, although it was pointed out yesterday
of course you could still take certain things to the מקוה, mikveh,
but this trick as it were of planting it and making it
go away, that doesn't apply. So that's the explanation by תרומה, Trumah,
that once תרומה Trumah was holy, when did רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan
say you could squeeze, I'm sorry, forget that, even though the תרומה
Trumah is, once תרומה Trumah is holy, yes planting it will make
the טומאה tumah go away, but that's for other purposes, for general
טומאה, tumah, but as far as the תרומה Trumah is concerned it
remains problematic. The same way this idea was said about water that
was going to be used for ניסוך המים, nisuch hamayim, that if
it became טמא tamei once it was already sanctified, you cannot plant
it in a מקוה, mikveh, immerse it in a מקוה mikveh for
it to become טהור. tahor. Fine. Now that is, so that was
yesterday's דף. daf. Now the גמרא Gemara wants to know, would this
idea that we give a special status to things that we don't
let them to be planted, this special idea, when things are holy,
we know that applies to תרומה Trumah that you sanctify, we know
it applies to water that's going to be used for the libations,
for the ניסוך, nisuch, but that was when it was put into
a holy vessel, a כלי שרת, kli sharet, and that gives it
the highest level of קדושה. kedushah. But things that are going to
be used for קרבנות korbanot that have been sanctified verbally but have
not yet been put in a כלי שרת, kli sharet, their level
of קדושה kedushah is not full. Would we still say that even
for those things, they're at this special status that you cannot use
this type of a trick? That was the question at the end
of yesterday.
And the answer was, well let's learn it out from this statement
of רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan who said that if you press
grapes that are sanctified, so let's actually pick up from there.
So the גמרא Gemara says like this, would have to I guess
read a little bit, we'll have to do it in order to
get back to where we were.
So the גמרא Gemara says I guess it's ten lines from the
bottom, so much we have to do just because we couldn't finish
to the משנה, Mishna, but we need the context. So the גמרא
Gemara says like this: כי אתא, Ki ata, so says אמר ליה
זיזו לא שמעתי כיוצא בזה שמעתי. Amar leh Zizu lo shamati kayotze
baze shamati.
Line starts with the word שמעתי. shamati. דאמר רבי אבהו אמר רבי
יוחנן ענבים שנטמאו דרכן ואחר כך הקדישן טהורים. Damar Rabbi Abbahu amar
Rabbi Yochanan anavim shenitme'u darchan ve'achar kach hikdishan tehorim. If you have
grapes that are טמא, tamei, if you first press them and then
you sanctify, that's טהור, tahor, because this is a different type of
a trick, not the trick of immersing in the מקוה mikveh or
planting, but the trick of doing less than the requisite amount at
any time, presumably that's the trick. So if it was before it
was sanctified, that's fine. הקדישן ואחר כך דרכן טמאים, Hikdishan ve'achar kach
darchan tme'im, but if they became טמא tamei after they were sanctified,
טמאים tme'im they're טמא. tamei. So similar idea that you can't use
certain tricks once something becomes טמא, tamei, once something is sanctified and
becomes טמא. tamei. Now what's the story of those grapes? So the
גמרא Gemara says והני ענבים דקדושת פה נינהו, Vahani anavim dekedushat peh
ninhu, presumably they were assuming that you wanted to use the grape
juice, the wine, for the altar. So it says but, as they're
still grapes they haven't been sanctified in a vessel, only the wine
is sanctified in a vessel. So even though it's only oral sanctification,
ואפילו הכי עבדו רבנן מעליא, Ve'afilu hachi avdu Rabbanan ma'alya, you see
that we don't allow tricks to be done even when the sanctification
is only oral. So the גמרא Gemara says no. אמר רב יוסף
ענבים קאמרת? Amar Rav Yosef anavim ka'amart? What grapes? We're not talking
about grapes that's going to be used for the wine for the
altar. הכא בענבים של תרומה עסקינן. Hacha be'anavim shel Trumah askinan. We're
talking about grapes of תרומה, Trumah, דקדושת פה דידו כקדושת כלי דמיא,
dekedushat peh didu kekedushat kli damya, that by תרומה Trumah the only
sanctification is a verbal one, so that's the highest level of קדושה,
kedushah, so we won't allow tricks by תרומה Trumah once it's been
sanctified. אבל הני דבעי כלי, Aval hani deba'ei kli, but something that
is sanctified for the altar that its full
sanctification...
maybe when it's only at a pre-level, at an oral sanctification, maybe
that would not make it so special that you can't use these,
that you can't use these special tricks. Okay, so that was what
we, how we ended that discussion about when you can use the
tricks or not, we're going to get back to it. But now
we get into this issue about, about the statement that you can
press the grapes without the juice becoming טמא. tamei. So the גמרא
Gemara says: דרכה ואפילו טובא? darcha v'afilu tuva? Wait a minute, this
recent statement of רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says you can press the
grapes and, and the juice won't become טמא, tamei, assuming that the
grapes haven't been sanctified yet. But he doesn't limit it, he says,
he just press them, presumably even a lot of grapes. ומי אמר
רבי יוחנן הכי? Umi amar Rabbi Yochanan hachi? Can he really say
that? ואמר רבי יוחנן, V'amar Rabbi Yochanan, and רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan
said: פחות מכביצה. pachos mi'kabaita. ואמר רבי יוחנן: V'amar Rabbi Yochanan: ענבים
שנטמאו דרכן פחות פחות מכביצה. anavim shenitmu darchan pachos pachos mi'kabaita. That
if you want to use this trick to get out the juice
without it becoming טמא, tamei, you have to do less than a
כביצה kabaita at any time. So how did this statement, which speaks
about sanctifying them before or after, not say that you're doing it
less than a כביצה? kabaita? The גמרא Gemara says: אי בעית אימא,
ee ba'is eima, if you want I could say: הכא נמי פחות
פחות מכביצה. hacha nami pachos pachos mi'kabaita. Here too, he means you
do the same trick, less than a כביצה. kabaita. ואי בעית אימא,
Ve'ee ba'is eima, and this is the answer we stopped short with
yesterday: התם, hatam, when do you have to do less than a
כביצה kabaita at any time? דנגעו להו בראשון. d'nagu lahu b'rishon. The
grapes touched a ראשון, rishon, so the grapes are a שני. sheni.
So if the grapes are a שני, sheni, if שני sheni touches
a liquid, the liquid becomes a ראשון. rishon. So again, we're talking
when does רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan say it works? It works before
you've sanctified it. Now before you've sanctified, food that's not sanctified and
not תרומה terumah and not קודש kodesh can only become a שני,
sheni, it cannot become lower than a שני. sheni. So if the
grapes are שני sheni and the liquid comes out, you would assume
the liquid is a שלישי, shlishi, you're safe regardless, but no, there's
a special exception to rule of liquids, that if a שני sheni
touches a liquid, a liquid becomes a ראשון. rishon. So when did
רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan say you have to do less than a
כביצה? kabaita? מדרבנן, mi'drabanan, that the grapes have touched a ראשון, rishon,
the grapes are שני, sheni, דהוו אינהו שני, d'havu inhu sheni,
the grapes are שני, sheni, and therefore if you do more than
a כביצה, kabaita, the liquid comes out, the liquid touches a שני,
sheni, becomes a ראשון, rishon, you got a problem. הכא דנגעו בשני,
hacha d'nagu b'sheni, this case the grapes touched a שני, sheni, דהוו
שלישי, d'havu shlishi, that the grapes are שלישי, shlishi, so therefore the
only way the liquid, so the liquid won't be a problem. If
it's all חולין, chullin, the liquid is non-problematic,
right? Because if it's all חולין, chullin, liquid cannot become a, anything
more than a שני, sheni, even the grapes really can't become a
שלישי. shlishi. So by the way, now we actually understand that the
reason it matters whether you sanctified them before or after has less
to do with this idea of using a trick of less than
a כביצה, kabaita, the issue of whether you sanctified them creating a
problem is because they've only touched a low-level טומאה, tumah, they've only
touched a שני, sheni, and if the grapes aren't sanctified, well non-sanctified
grapes don't become a שלישי. shlishi. So it's a completely different explanation
of how the whole thing works. Okay. אמר רבא, Amar Rava, let's
see,
it's interesting because by קדשים kodshim you can go up until even
a רביעי.
revi'i. Right. So if you sanctified them, right, exactly. אמר רבא: Amar
Rava: אף אנן נמי תנינא. af anan nami tanyina. Now we also
taught this idea that when things are at a higher level of,
when things are קודש kodesh or then they're, you can't use that
then there are certain you know tricks or whatever things that won't
work with them, even though they normally would work. We taught: ונתן
עליו מים חיים אל כלי. v'nasana alav mayim chayim el keli. That
you should put on it right the, that by the, by the
ashes of the פרה אדומה, parah adumah, water you know,
live water, water from a wellspring into the vessel. שתהא חיותן בכלי.
she'tehey chiyusan b'keli. That they have to be, their life has to
come in the vessel, meaning it has to be drawn directly in
the vessel. Okay, that's one דרשה.
derasha. Even used to sanctify it, means the vessel used...
Exactly, exactly. Okay,
so the vessel you're going to use to mix the ashes of
the פרה אדומה, parah adumah, that's the vessel you have to use
to draw the water. That's one דרשה. derasha. But then there's another
דרשה. derasha. ונתן. V'nasana. ונתן. V'nasana. על מתלושין Al matlushin it says
you place it into the vessel, which means that you drew the
water from a different vessel and then it's already uprooted and then
you're placing it into the vessel. Which is it? Do you have
to draw the water for the ashes of the פרה אדומה parah
adumah in the very vessel you're going to mix the ashes in,
or can you draw it from a different one? והא מחוברים נינהו.
V'ha michubarim inhu. So didn't we just say that you have to
draw them into the vessel from where they're attached, you can't take
them from somewhere else? אלא מעלה. Ella ma'alah. You know what, you're
right. Really the, the real פסוק pasuk is ונתן. v'nasana. You can
draw the water with another vessel and put it in this mixing
vessel. But the fact that we say it has to be drawn
directly with the vessel, that's a special stringency. So you see that
sometimes when you're dealing with קודש, kodesh, you know the, it has
these special stringencies. הכא נמי מעלה. Hacha nami ma'alah. Here too there's
a special stringency. Now it's a little bit of a funny analogy.
First of all, I mean it was already a funny analogy, we
went from זריעה zeri'ah to less than a כביצה, kabaita, but... Now
the whole thing is, is it really about, it's not the same
idea of once it's been sanctified versus after it's been sanctified or
before it's been sanctified. Very loose comparisons. Okay, and we're going to
see other comparisons that are even looser. Let's look. אמר רב שימי
בר אשי, Amar Rav Shimi bar Ashi, אף אנן נמי תנינא, af
anan nami tenina, we also taught similarly. טבל ועלה אוכל במעשר. Taval
ve'alah okhel bema'aser. If somebody goes to the מקוה Mikvah and they're
טמא, tamei, then they're טהור tahor now even before nightfall at least
for the purpose of מעשר. ma'aser. Really מעשר ma'aser you don't need
to be טהור. tahor. הערב שמש Ha'arev shemesh once it's nightfall, אוכל
בתרומה, okhel betrumah, then you're טהור tahor enough and you can eat
תרומה. trumah. בתרומה אין בקדשים לא. Betrumah in bekodshim lo. Yes you
can eat תרומה trumah but not קדשים, kodshim, even if the end
of the process has to be like bringing a קרבן korban the
next morning, like you know, so אמאי, amai, now why is that?
טהור הוא, Tahor hu, you're טהור. tahor. Why should there be this
distinction? I mean this is a general הלכה. halakhah. People that have
to bring a קרבן korban the next morning as part of their
טהרה taharah process, by nightfall after they've gone to the מקוה Mikvah
they're טהור tahor enough for תרומה, trumah, but the קרבן korban is
required like to in order like a woman after childbirth let's say,
you know, a קרבן korban is required or זב וזבה zav ve'zavah
to order to be able to eat קרבנות. korbanot. So why is
that? Why do you need another קרבן? korban? Isn't it enough that
you've gone to the מקוה? Mikvah? אלא מעלה, Ela ma'alah, it's a
special level. הכא נמי מעלה, Hakha nami ma'alah, here too. Now this
is getting to be crazy these comparisons because that's a דאורייתא. De'oraisa.
Biblically, the way חזל Chazal right, you need a קרבן korban the
next morning to be fully טהור. tahor. But we're saying is ah,
you see that the תורה Torah when it comes to eating קרבנות
korbanot makes extra demands. It's not enough to be טהור tahor having
gone to the מקוה, Mikvah, you have to bring a קרבן. korban.
So here too we're going to make—fine, but like it's such a
different reality. One is you remove the level of טהרה taharah required
for you to be able to eat a קרבן korban versus you
to be able to eat תרומה. trumah. And we were comparing that
to the question of whether a process of transforming something, planting it
in the ground, works for חולין chullin versus working for תרומה. trumah.
Like you know, it's like such loose comparisons. Oh, we see in
one place the תורה Torah is more מחמיר machmir by קדשים, kodshim,
so that'll explain why we have this חומרא chumra that these tricks
don't work. Okay, anyway, אמר רב אשי, Amar Rav Ashi, רב אשי
Rav Ashi says אף אנן נמי תנינא, af anan nami tenina, we
also still taught similarly. והבשר, Vehabasar, we had this דרשה drashah also
a little while ago, and the meat that you know that can
become, you know only טהור tahor people can eat. So what's the
extra vav? לרבות את העצים והלבונה, Lirabot et ha'etzim vehalevona, that even
frankincense and wood can become טמא tamei if they're sanctified. Now that's
already a little bit more similar because it is sanctified, the טומאה
tumah more adheres to it, even though normally טומאה tumah would only
adhere to vessels or to food. עצים ולבונה בני טומאה נינהו Etzim
vehalevona benei tumah ninhu? Is wood and frankincense something that can really
become טמא? tamei? אלא מעלה, Ela ma'alah, you see it's a higher
level. Again, according to most that's a דאורייתא. De'oraisa. I mean there's
a question you know, but it seems it could even be biblical.
But nevertheless you see biblically because it's קדש, kodesh, the טומאה tumah
more adheres to it. הכא נמי מעלה, Hakha nami ma'alah, here too,
because the תרומה trumah or whatever the water for ניסוך המים nisukh
hamayim is קדש, kodesh, the טומאה tumah more adheres to it and
these tricks won't remove the טומאה tumah as easily. Okay, so that
was the end of the very loose comparisons at the end, but
that ends our very long discussion about טומאה tumah and תרומה trumah
and all these things that we digressed on because of a משנה,
mishna, I don't even remember anymore because what was the משנה mishna
originally talking about?
Oh, תרומה trumah eating תרומה חמץ trumah chametz on פסח Pesach and
that led us to these discussions. Now we have a radical shift.
After all of that, look, other than even the digressions, basically until
now for the first thirty-odd pages, we've been talking about the איסור,
issur, the prohibition of owning חמץ, chametz, right? Owning חמץ chametz and
therefore you have to do בדיקה, bedikah, owning חמץ chametz from חצות
chatzot on, getting rid of your חמץ chametz rabbinically, starting at what
time can you not eat it, whether you get rid of your
חמץ chametz by burning it, by crumbling it up, right? All these
things have been about owning חמץ. chametz. If you own חמץ chametz
and it's אסור בהנאה, assur behana'ah, חמץ שעבר עליו הפסח. chametz she'avar
alav haPesach. And then the last couple of discussions were if a
non-Jew owned חמץ, chametz, then after פסח Pesach it's מותר בהנאה, muttar
behana'ah, but all of this has been about owning חמץ. chametz. Okay,
it's been about the חמץ chametz issue. Now we shift—don't worry we're
not done with חמץ chametz because we're going to get back—but now
we shift, a very radical shift, to actually the מצוות mitzvot of
פסח Pesach and the מצווה mitzvah of מצה matzah and מרור. maror.
Okay, so a real big shift comes up now in this משנה.
mishna. Let's read this משנה. mishna. Well, you could just say we're
done with one topic, but the thing is we are going to
get back to it. I don't know, we'll worry about it then.
Let's take a look at this משנה. mishna.
I'm waiting for the משנה mishna about having to line everything with
aluminum foil.
Okay, yeah, that's coming up. No no. אלו דברים שאדם יוצא בהן
ידי חובתו בפסח. Elu devarim she'adam yotzei bahen yedei chovato bePesach. The
following things you fulfill your obligation on פסח, Pesach, meaning your obligation
of מצה. matzah. בחיטין בשעורים, Bechittin bise'orin, you have to make מצה
matzah out of the following
things: with wheat, with barley, בכוסמין בשיפון ובשיבולת שועל, bechusmin bishifon uvishibollet
shu'al, and three other grains. Now how are those—what are those three
other grains? So there's a wonderful blog posting
on—What?
You have pictures on there?
Yeah, but then I would have to turn... Anyway, there's this wonderful
blog posting that I wrote on this site called the Daily דף.
Daf. Actually no, I actually was rereading it, I wrote this over
a year ago, but it's actually, it's actually a very good blog
posting about this issue of the five grains. Normally these are translated
as כוסמין chusmin as spelt,
שיפון shifon as rye, and שיבולת שועל shibolet shual as oats. Okay,
spelt, rye, and oats. That's the normal translation given, a lot of
that is based on רש"י. Rashi. Okay, but we're going to get
back to that in a minute. And the assumption being why these
five? We know that these are the classic five, and the assumption
is that only these five are actually can the stuff be מחמיץ.
machmitz.
Can you make מוציא? motzi? Can they be מחמיץ, machmitz, can they
ferment? And if they can and if only these can be ferment
and be מחמיץ, machmitz, then similarly only them can you make מצה
matzah out of. Because there's a link, by the way, just think
about the idea that חמץ chametz and מצה matzah are almost the
exact same letters, right? מצה Matzah and חמץ, chametz, only difference ח
chet and the ה, hei, whatever, clearly and the תורה Torah links
them, right? Don't eat חמץ, chametz, eat מצה. matzah. They're both called
לחם. lechem. So the idea is only these five create לחם, lechem,
bread, presumably because only five of them have the potential to ferment,
although מצה matzah you don't allow to ferment. So therefore you can
only make מצה matzah out of these five grains. I'll talk in
a little bit about what exactly those grains are. ויוצאין V'yotzin now,
beyond the grains, what about the status of the grains?
ויוצאין בדמאי ובמעשר ראשון שנטלה תרומתו. V'yotzin b'demai u'v'maaser rishon shenatla terumaso.
If the grains were דמאי, demai, meaning it was stuff you bought
from an עם הארץ, am ha'aretz, you don't know if תרומות ומעשרות
terumos u'maasros have been taken from it, so rabbinically you can—biblically there's
a רוב rov that it has, but rabbinically you're not allowed to
eat from it. Nevertheless, if you made your מצה matzah out of
those out of that grain without taking your תרומות ומעשרות, terumos u'maasros,
you're still יוצא yotze because it was דמאי, demai, it was doubtful.
ובמעשר ראשון שנטלה תרומתו, U'v'maaser rishon shenatla terumaso, if it was מעשר
maaser given to a לוי levi and then the תרומה terumah because
from the לוי's levi מעשר, maaser, he takes another tenth, a tenth
of a tenth, called תרומת מעשר terumas maaser and gives it to
the כהן. kohen. Before that it's טבל. tevel. Once he takes this
tenth of a tenth, it's חולין chulin and anybody can eat from
it. So therefore the גמרא's Gemara going to ask what the חידוש
chiddush is. So once the מעשר ראשון maaser rishon has the תרומה
terumah taken from it, you can make you can use that grain.
ובמעשר שני והקדש שנפדו, U'v'maaser sheni v'hekdesh shenifdu, or מעשר שני maaser
sheni or הקדש hekdesh that was sanctified but then redeemed, okay? So
again, what's the חידוש? chiddush? Now it's חולין. chulin. Okay, whatever. Anyway,
but nevertheless although they had that quasi status, it's now not problematic
and you can go ahead and use it for your מצה. matzah.
And here's a חידוש, chiddush, bigger חידוש, chiddush, והכהנים והקד... והכהנים, v'hakohanim
v'hekd... v'hakohanim, the כהנים kohanim can use for מצה matzah בחלה ובתרומה.
b'challah u'v'terumah. מצה Matzah made out of grain
that was given to them as חלה challah or as תרומה. terumah.
Even though it's something that cannot be eaten by non-כהנים, kohanim, it
doesn't matter. Since it doesn't have to be מצה matzah doesn't have
something that's universally eatable. As long as the כהנים kohanim are allowed
to eat it, it has a status of תרומה terumah and they're
the ones eating it, then they're
יוצא. yotze. אבל לא, Aval lo, but you're not יוצא yotze בטבל,
b'tevel, real טבל tevel as opposed to דמאי, demai, ולא במעשר ראשון
שלא נטלה תרומתו, v'lo b'maaser rishon shelo natla terumaso, or מעשר ראשון
maaser rishon of the לוי levi that the other tenth wasn't given
from it, the tenth of a tenth, because then it's also טבל.
tevel. ולא במעשר שני והקדש שלא נפדו, V'lo b'maaser sheni v'hekdesh shelo
nifdu, and not מעשר שני maaser sheni again which is eaten in
the first, second, fourth, and fifth years in ירושלים yerushalayim and outside
ירושלים yerushalayim cannot be eaten unless it's redeemed, or הקדש hekdesh or
general sanctified things that have not been redeemed. These are not allowed
to be eaten.
הגמרא's Hagemara also going to explain why.
Okay, yeah. Now, so all those, so basically you're not יוצא yotze
with things that are אסור assur to be eaten. Why is what's
the reason for that? We'll talk in a minute, but that's the
basic principle. Now, here's another weird הלכה. halacha. חלות התודה ורקיקי נזיר,
Challos hatoda v'rekikei nazir, if you have somebody baked
מצות matzos to be used for a תודה. toda. Now the תודה
toda is for a thanksgiving קרבן korban that had thirty חלות challos
of מצה matzah and ten חלות challos of חמץ. chametz. So we're
not talking about the חמץ chametz ones. You baked the חלות challos
to be used for the תודה. toda. Now, or you baked wafers
to be used for a נזיר. nazir. Now the point here being
not that you already sanctified them, because then you'd have to be
what? Eating them in the בית המקדש beis hamikdash on פסח pesach
night? No, we're talking that you baked them, you baked them for
this purpose, but you have yet to sanctify them. עשאן לעצמו, Asan
l'atzmo,
if you made them for yourself to bring as a קרבן, korban,
you had a תודה toda or a נזיר nazir קרבן korban you
had to bring, אין יוצא בהן, ein yotze bahen, you can't use
them even if you haven't sanctified them. עשאן למכור בשוק, Asan limkor
bashuk, if you did them to sell in the marketplace, יוצא בהן,
yotze bahen, you can, you know, to sell them to other people
who needed to bring them for קרבנות, korbanos, you knew that there
was a that a lot of people were נזירים nezirim this week
and there was going to be a big market on נזיר nazir
wafers. So you baked the נזיר nazir wafers to sell them to
נזירים. nezirim. Okay? So in that case, before you sanctified them, you
can use them. So the question is like if you haven't sanctified
them yet, why should it matter? What should be the problem? So
all these things we're going to unpack. Let's start with the גמרא
Gemara and first look at the issue of the types of grain,
which is I think the more relevant question.
תנא, Tana, so... כוסמין מין חיטין. Kusmin min chitin. כוסמין Kusmin spelt
is a type of of grain, of of wheat, okay? שיבולת שועל
Shibolet Shual I'm going to give this the standard translation and then
I'll talk about it, oats,
ושיפון veshiphon and rye is מין שעורים min seorim is a type
of barley. Now we're going to say what these things are. כוסמין
Kusmin is גולבא gulba which is some Aramaic word which is, okay,
שיפון shiphon דישרא dishra and שיבולת שועל shibolet shual is שבילי תעלא
shivile taala which is just a direct translation of שיבולת שועל shibolet
shual which basically means like the, you know, the rows of a
fox, the hair the hairs of a fox. Okay, so those are
they. Now, what are those things? I gave them translation of spelt,
oats, and rye, but now I'm going to read to you from
my blog from a while ago. Okay, so here I'll read to
you very briefly here, but I just it was written here better
than I could say it now. When it comes to שיפון, shiphon,
right, that was the one that we translated as rye, רש"י Rashi
translates as סיגלא sigla which is rye. However, rye was unknown in
the land of Israel and cannot be right. Dr. Yehuda Felix, author
of flora and fauna in the משנה, Mishna, concludes that שיפון shiphon
is Triticum spelta or spelt. So we have spelt, except rather than
saying that it's rye, which is רש"י Rashi says, okay, he says
that it
is—I mean, we have spelt, except rather than רש"י Rashi who says
spelt is כוסמין, kusmin, he says spelt is שיפון. shiphon. What's the
other one? Calm down. Okay, spelt is technically a form of wheat,
and we have the גמרא Gemara says that שיפון shiphon is a
type of barley. It's many characteristics similar to barley and commonly used
as an alternative to barley of animal feed. Okay, so that's שיפון,
shiphon, which is saying that שיפון shiphon is not rye, it's spelt.
So we've got spelt at least. Now, כוסמין, kusmin, which the גמרא
Gemara said was a type of wheat and רש"י Rashi said was
spelt, can't be spelt anymore, okay, Dr. Felix concludes that it is
כוסמת, kusemet, which is emmer wheat, okay, which was used in the
land of Israel even in the First Temple period. This wheat was
one of the earliest cultivated forms of wheat. Okay, so that works
out very well. So now you've got כוסמין, kusmin, which is a
type of wheat, which actually is a type of wheat, it's emmer
wheat. Okay, you've got שיפון, shiphon, which is—what did we say שיפון
shiphon was?—which was spelt, okay, and now we're left with שיבולת שועל.
shibolet shual. And what we haven't included is rye. So what's שיבולת
שועל? shibolet shual? Okay,
so anyway, so the problem with saying that it is... that it
is... that it's the one that we haven't said yet, which is
rye, is because rye doesn't have gluten, right? And presumably, one of—what
all the other grains have, and also a difference between those grains
and rice, which we're about to say is not חמץ, chametz, is
that those grains have gluten. But rye also doesn't have gluten. Okay,
so... wait a minute... I mean, not rye, what's the one we
haven't included? Oats!
I'm sorry. Oats do not have—oats, right, right.
Oats do not have gluten, right. So therefore, Felix, Dr. Felix says
that it is a type of a two-row barley. So basically what
you have is the following. According to—I know. So according to Dr.
Felix, which is כוסמין מין חיטין, kusmin min chitin, כוסמין kusmin is
emmer wheat, שיבולת שועל shibolet shual is two-row barley, and שיפון shiphon
is spelt, which looks like and is used like barley, and those
are types of barley. That's his identification. And for him, rye is
not on the list. A, because it doesn't work, and B, it
doesn't have the common denominator of all these things, which is gluten.
So for him, rye is not on the list. Now, this is
a non-trivial discussion because people that
cannot—celiac—celiacs that cannot handle gluten, what they use for פסח, Pesach, for
מצה, matzah, is spelt—no, but
spelt has—spelt has gluten!
Not in spelt. So they use rye! No, oat! Oat! I keep
on missaying it. Oats, oats, right, right. Oats, oats. Okay, you're right,
you're right. I thought I was reading by my thing because I
keep on... Okay, thank you, thank you. That's why I was reading
from my thing because I keep on missaying it. Okay, let's try
again. Okay.
According to רש"י, Rashi, you have spelt, rye, and oats in the
list. I know, I kept on missaying, according to רש"י, Rashi, you
have spelt, rye, and oats. Oats don't have gluten. According to, you
know, a more scholarly approach, you don't have spelt, rye, and oats,
you have spelt, two-row barley, and emmer wheat. Okay, so now excluding
rye from the list is not a big deal because rye
was unknown in the ancient land
of—rye was unknown ancient land. What is also not a big deal
practically?
Pure rye also doesn't have gluten.
Okay, fine. Okay, but let's focus on it. But excluding oats, right,
is the most problematic because there's a logic to exclude it, that
it doesn't have gluten, but the reality then is that celiacs now
eat oat-based מצה matzah to be יוצא yotzei because of that identification.
But if we go... Which is all based on רש״י Rashi *Rashi*,
but if we go by this more academic identification, rye and oats
are off list, and oats being off list gives you a problem.
So what is the story? So I'll read you a story that
is in Wikipedia actually. Okay, under Hebrew Wikipedia under חמישה מיני דגן
dagan, *Chamisha Minei Dagan*. It's amazing what you can find in Hebrew
Wikipedia. Professor Felix relates that on the basis of his identification, רב
שלמה זלמן אויערבך *Rav Shlomo Zalman Auerbach* used to make the ברכה
*beracha* of שהכל *Shehakol* on his morning breakfast of oatmeal because oats
are no longer a grain, so he would make שהכל *Shehakol* on
it like you'd make it on Rice Krispies or something. Okay, he
did this for two years until רב שלמה אלישיב *Rav Shlomo Elyashiv*
yelled at him with the critique that one cannot change what has
been the Jewish custom for hundreds of years, going back to the
time of the ראשונים Rishonim *Rishonim* just because of one scholar, because
Felix decided, just because of science. So this is a very interesting
issue about science and הלכה Halacha. *halacha*, but there is a reality,
you know, that הלכה *halacha* works within its sort of legal realities.
How much is it revised based on sort of scientific findings is
an ongoing question, but it doesn't automatically change just because, you know,
some of the facts are discovered. There's a certain question of legal
realities. It's also questions about like when we פסקן pasken *pasken* based
on the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*'s interpretation of the משנה Mishna *Mishnah*, even
if it might not have been the original interpretation of the משנה
mishna. *Mishnah*. There's a question of sort of legally canonized, the canonized
work of the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* legally binding meanings. Now that might
disturb you, we should just revise it because we know now what
those grains have to be, but the reality is that it's very
important that we פסקן *pasken* that oats are a type of a
grain, besides that you make מזונות *mezonos* on oatmeal, it's very relevant
because it allows celiacs to have מצה matzah, *matzah* on פסח Pesach.
*Pesach*. Okay, so that's in terms of these grains, which again רש״י
Rashi *Rashi* says is rye, oats, and spelt. According to Dr. Felix,
it is the כוסמין *kusmin* is emmer wheat, שיבולת שועל *shibolet shual*
and שיפון *shifon* is spelt and a type of a two-row barley,
and the issue being that rye and oats would not be on
the list and particularly oats would not be on the list. Okay,
but we actually פסקן *pasken* that oats are included. So now the
גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* continues, two lines, and this will get to also
this difference about what things are considered grains or not. הני אין
*hani in*, these things yes, אורז Orez ודוחן לא *orez
vedochen lo*. אורז *orez* and דוחן *dochen* are not, which is rice
and millet, are not considered grains. מנא הני מילי *minani mili*, where
do you get this from? אמר רב שמעון בן לקיש *Amar Rav
Shimon ben Lakish*, וכן תנא tana דבי רבי ישמעאל *vechen tana d'bei
Rabi Yishmael*, וכן תנא דבי רבי אליעזר בן יעקב *vechen tana d'bei
Rabi Eliezer ben Yaakov*, אמר קרא *amar kra*, the פסוק pasuk *pasuk*
says, לא תאכל עליו חמץ chametz. *lo tochal alav chametz*, don't eat
חמץ chametz? *chametz*, שבעת ימים תאכל עליו מצות matzos, *shivat yamim tochal
alav matzot*, eat מצה matzah. *matzah*. דברים *Devarim*, so this is where
you get the whole idea that only certain things can become מצה
matzah, *matzah* because of its link to חמץ chametz. *chametz*. As I
said also the words are almost the same. דברים הבאים לידי חימוץ
*Devarim habaim lidei chimutz*, things that can become חמץ chametz. *chametz*, אדם
יוצא yotzei ידי חובתו במצה *adam yotzei yedei chovato b'matzah*, is מצה
matzah, *matzah* when you don't let it ferment. יצאו אלו
*Yatzu elu*, it excludes rice and millet, which allows the five things
on the list but excludes rice and millet, שאין באין לידי חימוץ
*she-ein ba'in lidei chimutz*, that do not ferment, אלא לידי סירחון *ela
lidei sirchon*, they rather somehow spoil. Now, or they, you know, they
decompose. Now what does this mean that rice does not בא לידי
חימוץ *ba lidei chimutz*? So the normal, the normal, you know, translation
of חימוץ *chimutz* is ferment, but rice ferments, does ferment. Okay, it
breaks down and whatever the sugars break down etc it ferments. Rice
vinegar, right. So what does not happen with rice, what does not
happen with rice that happens with these things? So there, you know,
there whatever contemporary, you know, rabbis and scholars trying to figure out
what line the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is drawing and points out to
two differences. One is what I said, that rice doesn't have gluten
and these things, the other things do, and the presence of gluten
allows you to sort of like, you know, mold the dough, knead
the dough, it gives it like a, you know, a sort of
it holds it together, it holds it together, it's like a glue
and it makes it sort of more elastic and shapable. But of
course why that would be considered בא לידי חימוץ *ba lidei chimutz*,
that's more about the, you know, the kneading of the dough than
the process of חמץ chametz. *chametz*. So the other explanation given, I
you know I did some research on the web on this is,
not fermenting, but what we more as like בעלי בתים *balabatim* would
call חמץ chametz *chametz*, you know, sort of a lay perspective which
is the releasing of gas that happens in the process of, you
know, when you bring the water and the flour together and that
causes the thing to like puff up. Okay, so that if you
actually mix rice flour with water, okay, will technically will fermenting happen?
Yes, but it won't be the same case about like a lot
of gas releasing and the flour puffing up. Okay so that might
be what חז״ל *Chazal*... yeah, of course if it does, right, and
that's the whole idea of חמץ chametz, *chametz* again from a lay
person that's what חמץ chametz. *chametz* is. It's about the sort of
rising of the dough and that presumably does not happen with rice
and millet. Whether it happens with oats...
I can show you on the web people have done studies and
they whatever and that actually yes...
when you take rice and you cook it it does puff up.
To the same, I mean in a significant way?
If you bake rice it it looks...
is different when cooked. I'm not saying it doesn't look different, but
if you make, if you make rice dough and you, you know,
and you leave it on the table and you, and you come
back an hour later—and now... I'll tell you, somebody, somebody did, they
had a scientist do studies on this. Make rice dough, leave it
on table, come back an hour later, and make flour dough with,
you know, and leave it and come back an hour later. The
difference about how one has risen and the other has not, okay?
And I think that's a reasonable explanation. Whether where oats falls in
that going back to that question is a different issue, but this
is the גמרא'ס idea. And of course then becomes the whole, the
whole חומרא chumra of the אשכנזים Ashkenazim about rice being, you know,
קטניות, kitniyos, which is a separate discussion where that comes from. But
basically it comes from this, two things: number one is because it
is easily confusable, although the גמרא Gemara says you could take, keep
the difference, but because, you know, what makes rice different than, you
know, both you can make flour and dough out of it, and
also because when they sold, you know, rice, often it might have
had other flowers mixed up, you know, or other grains mixed up
into it. Anyway, led to the whole אשכנזי Ashkenazi חומרא chumra of
קטניות, kitniyos, which we're not going to talk about.
But you make rice bread?
I know. So right, so now the גמרא Gemara continues, okay, so
it says like this: מתניתין דלא כרבי יוחנן בן נורי. Masnitin d'lo
k'Rabbi Yochanan ben Nuri. The משנה Mishnah is not like רבי יוחנן
בן נורי. Rabbi Yochanan ben Nuri. דאמר אורז מין דגן הוא. D'amar
orez min dagan hu. He actually says rice is a form of
דגן, of grain. וחייבין על חימוצו כרת, V'chayavin al chimutzo kares, and
you're חייב כרת. chayav kares. דתניא תנו רבנן, Detanya tanu rabanan, רבי
יוחנן בן נורי Rabbi Yochanan ben Nuri אוסר באורז ודוחן. oser b'orez
v'dochan. He forbids one to use rice or millet for like, to
say, like, meaning, to allow it to, you know, to not, you
know, to allow a dish made out of it that wasn't treated
as מצה, matzah that wasn't baked immediately. He says you cannot go
ahead and use it. מפני שקרוב להחמיץ, Mipnei she'karov l'hachmitz, because it
will, it's close to becoming חמץ. chametz And what does that mean?
איבעיא להו, Ibayu lehu, we ask the question. שקרוב להחמיץ, She'karov l'hachmitz,
what does it mean close to becoming חמץ? chametz. דקדים ומחמיץ? Dekadim
u'machmitz? Does that mean that it'll be, it'll ferment even quicker than
flour, so it's even more strict? או דלמא, O dilma, or what
it means is, דלמא קרוב להחמיץ הוי. dilma karov l'hachmitz havei. It's
close to חמץ. chametz, It's, it's almost חמץ. chametz, אבל חמץ גמור
לא הוי, Aval chametz gamur lo havei, it's not full חמץ. chametz.
Meaning we have a category called חמץ נוקשה chametz nuksha of things
that haven't really like fully fermented, and maybe that's what he is
saying is the case of rice. So he says rice is a
problem, but how big of a problem is it? So תא שמע,
Ta shma, come in here. דתניא, Detanya, we taught in a ברייתא.
braisa. אמר רבי יוחנן בן נורי, Amar Rabbi Yochanan ben Nuri, אורז
מין דגן הוא. Orez min dagan hu. אורז is rice is a
type of grain. וחייבין על חימוצו כרת. V'chayavin al chimutzo kares. And
if you actually let it become חמץ chametz and you don't bake
it, I mean obviously you could bake it the same way you
bake flour מצות, matzahs, but if you don't bake it soon enough
and it becomes חמץ, chametz you get כרת kares for it. ואדם
יוצא בו ידי חובתו בפסח. V'adam yotzei bo yedei chovato b'Pesach. And
if you do bake it, you can use it for מצה. matzah
You know, if you do, וכן היה רבי יוחנן בן נורי אומר.
v'chen haya Rabbi Yochanan ben Nuri omer. Now, that proves that קרוב
להחמיץ karov l'hachmitz does not mean it's quasi-חמץ. chametz It means it
actually becomes חמץ chametz quicker. Because according to him rice is a
full חמץ. chametz. You get כרת kares for it, which proves it's
full חמץ, chametz? and if you made it into מצה, matzah. you
can use it. Now, one other identification. וכן אמר רבי יוחנן בן
נורי אומר, V'chen amar Rabbi Yochanan ben Nuri omer, קרמית חייבת בחלה.
karmis chayaves b'chala. קרמית Karmis is obligated in חלה. challa. מאי קרמית?
Mai karmis? What is this
קרמית? karmis? אמר אביי, Amar Abaye, שצניתא. shatznisa. מאי שצניתא? Mai shatznisa?
What's this? אמר רב פפא, Amar Rav Papa, שצניתא דמשתכחא ביני כלניסא,
shatznisa d'mishtachacha beinei kalnisa, כלניסא. kalnisa. So it's the שצניתא shatznisa that
can be found between the כלניסא, kalnisa, which go figure this out.
Anyway, רש"י Rashi says it's a type of a weed or type
of I don't know some type of a thing that's basically like
millet. And therefore the same way rice and millet are חמץ, chametz?
this type of a grain also or legume also is חמץ. chametz.
They were saying the fennel flower?
The fennel flower. Okay, Artscroll usually does not identify, but maybe feels
it's safe to identify here because we don't פסקן that way. Okay,
anyway, moving on. So now what do we have? Five grains are
חמץ chametz and מצה, matzah, others not. The difference between whether they're
מחמיץ, machmitz, which is almost tautology. We've said מחמיץ machmitz might relate
to the gluten or might relate to the idea of the releasing
gases and the rising. Rice is not in that category, it does
ferment, but it doesn't become חמץ chametz if we define it that
way. These other things are. We mentioned the issue of oats and
their classic identification in the five, but the possibility that they don't
really belong there. Okay, and now we move on to another and
related point.
Okay, אמר רבה בר בר חנה אמר ריש לקיש, Amar Rabbah bar
bar Chana amar Reish Lakish, עיסה. issa. So we're covering a lot
of things. What are the grains? The issue of rice. And now
we get to one other major category about חמץ chametz. and מצה
matzah that's very relevant today. אמר ריש לקיש, Amar Reish Lakish, עיסה
שנילושה ביין ושמן ודבש. issa shenilsha b'yayin v'shemen u'devash.
Let's say you didn't use water. You use what's called מי פירות,
mei peiros, fruit juices. Used wine and oil and honey, although I
do recognize that honey is not a fruit juice. But you used
liquids other than water. Unless it means דבש תמרים, dvash tmarim, unless
it means date honey, and then it is a fruit juice. Anyway,
אין חייבין על חימוצה כרת. ein chayavin al chimutza kares. That does
not really become חמץ chametz even if you let it outside. Now,
he doesn't get כרת. kares. It's just מצה עשירה. matzah ashira. Now,
well, yeah. מצה עשירה matzah ashira is a different question, but the
רי"ף Rif goes even further that it doesn't even become חמץ. chametz
Now, at least not to get
כרת. kares. So יתיב רב פפא ורב הונא בריה דרב יהושע קמיה
דרב אידי בר אבין, yasiv Rav Pappa veRav Huna breih deRav Yehoshua
kammai deRav Idi bar Avin, so they were sitting in front of
רב אידי בר אבין. Rav Idi bar Avin. ויתיב רב אידי בר
אבין וקאמנמנם, veyasiv Rav Idi bar Avin vekamnamnem, and רב אידי בר
אבין Rav Idi bar Avin was, you know, nodding off. He was
dozing. So אמר ליה רב הונא בריה דרב יהושע לרב פפא, amar
lei Rav Huna breih deRav Yehoshua leRav Pappa, so רב הונא Rav
Huna the son of רב יהושע Rav Yehoshua said to רב פפא,
Rav Pappa, מאי טעמא דריש לקיש? mai taama deReish Lakish? What's the
reason of ריש לקיש Reish Lakish that, you know, that things made
with fruit juices is not treated as real חמץ? chametz. So I
mean, obviously it has a water content, why should it not be
treated as real חמץ? chametz So אמר ליה דאמר קרא, amar lei
de'amar kra, so he says, so he said to him, like what
we were thinking, because the פסוק pasuk says לא תאכל עליו חמץ
שבעת ימים תאכל עליו מצות. lo sachal alav chametz shivas yamim tochal
alav matzos. So until now we've been saying the only thing you
can use for מצה matzah is something that has the potential to
become חמץ. chametz He's going to make the link the opposite way.
The only thing that's חמץ chametz. is something that could become מצה.
matzah Okay, what does that mean? So דברים שאדם יוצא ידי חובתו
במצה, devarim she'adam yoizei yedei chovaso bematzah, only something that in theory
you could use for מצה, matzah חייבין על חימוצו כרת, chayavin al
chimutzo kares, do you get as is treated as full חמץ chametz,
that you get
כרת. kares. והא האי ואין אדם יוצא בו ידי חובתו, veha hai
ve'ein adam yoizei bo yedei chovaso, since if you baked this you
would not be able to use it for מצה matzah with fruit
juices. Why not? דהוה ליה מצה עשירה, dehava lei matzah ashira, because
one of the categories of מצה matzah is לחם עוני, lechem oni,
poor person's bread. If it's made with all these sweet fruit juices,
it's no longer poor person's bread, it's a nice delicacy. So since
you couldn't make a מצה matzah out of it, אין חייבין על
חימוצו כרת, ein chayavin al chimutzo kares, you don't get כרת kares
for it's not treated as full חמץ. chametz Which seems like a
wild idea, right? Because מצה matzah, presumably has the base criteria is
it has to be made out of the grains that could ferment,
and then we might add other criteria to it. It's got to
be לחם עוני, lechem oni, whatever. Maybe it has to be made
לשמה. lishma. Would you say that if you didn't do it לשמה
lishma you wouldn't get כרת? kares? I mean the idea, right, it
doesn't make so much sense to say that the extra criteria of
מצה matzah somehow effect whether this if it's חמץ chametz. whether it's
really treated as serious חמץ chametz or not. But that's his argument.
איתיביה רב הונא בריה דרב יהושע לרב פפא, eisivei Rav Huna breih
deRav Yehoshua leRav Pappa, so he challenged that idea that only something
that would be treated as מצה matzah. do you get is also
fully treated as
חמץ. chametz. המחהו וגמעו, hemcheiyu ugemao, if you baked say ahead like
sort of like submerged this מצה matzah, or the bread in water,
you sort of liquefied it and then you swallowed it. אם חמץ
הוא וענוש כרת, im chametz hu ve'onesh kares, if it's חמץ chametz
you still get כרת kares
for, was dissolved?
Yeah, dissolved. So if it's חמץ chametz. you still get כרת kares
for eating this dissolved bread.
ואם מצה היא אין אדם יוצא בה ידי חובתו בפסח, ve'im matzah
hi ein adam yoizei bah yedei chovaso bePesach, it's not you don't
do the מצוה mitzvah אכילת מצה בפסח. achilas matzah bePesach.
I'm sure he'd have גבורות? Gevuros?
Right, obviously he'd have גבורות Gevuros in the גמרא. Gemara. Okay, but
yes, so והא הכא, ve'ha hacha, here's a case דאין אדם יוצא
בו ידי חובתו במצה, de'ein adam yoizei bo yedei chovaso bematzah, you
can't use it for מצה, matzah וחייבין על חימוצו כרת, vechayavin al
chimutzo kares, and you still get כרת kares for חמץ. chametz, So
clearly yes, מצה matzah has to be something that could be חמץ,
chametz. but to be חמץ chametz it doesn't have to have all
the qualities of being מצה. matzah So אתער בהו רב אידי בר
אבין, is'ar behu Rav Idi bar Avin, so רב אידי בר אבין
Rav Idi bar Avin woke up in the middle of this discussion.
You know somehow his unconscious brain was processing this discussion and realized
that they were like off track. אמר להו amar lehu he said
to them דרדקי, dardekei, children. You really wonder how old they were
that he was calling them children but okay. Is it a term
of
endearment or is he just insulting them?
No, no, it's a term of endearment. היינו טעמא דריש לקיש, hainu
taama deReish Lakish, here's the reason of ריש לקיש Reish Lakish about
the fruit juices. משום דהוה ליה מי פירות, mishum dehava lei mei
peiros, because it's made with fruit juices ומי פירות אין מחמיצין. umei
peiros ein machmitzin. Fruit juice does not make things חמץ.
chametz Is that true?
Now, I don't know scientifically again about this although I will show
you to this website I found yesterday that they had this scientist
do these experiments about, you know, doing doing this type of thing,
the flour with the fruit juices and so on. The sugar might
affect exactly the chemical process and presumably, if we go back to
this idea that חמץ chametz. means the releasing of gas and the
blowing up of the dough, I think that from the at least
this thing I read on the web, it does not happen the
same way with fruit juices. So that's an interesting experiment you could
try at home. So this is the principle that fruit juices don't
make חמץ. chametz Now, what does it mean אין מחמיצין? ein machmitzin?
Because ריש לקיש Reish Lakish said you don't get כרת. kares. So
it's possible to say it's not full חמץ chametz, but it's this
חמץ נוקשה, chametz nuksha, this quasi חמץ. chametz. Okay, there's other גמרות
Gemaras that make the and there's actually contradictory evidence in the גמרות.
Gemaras. Some גמרות Gemaras make it sound like it doesn't become full
חמץ, chametz it becomes quasi חמץ. chametz Others גמרות Gemaras make it
sound like it doesn't become חמץ chametz, at all. So there are
two basic positions in the ראשונים Rishonim. about fruit juices. One is
that all fruit juices are problem and because it doesn't become full
חמץ chametz, but it becomes quasi חמץ. chametz. And therefore you wouldn't
be able to? No, if you baked it within 18 minutes or
if you baked it immediately whatever, you know, there's actually a גמרא
that makes it sound it might become חמץ chametz. even faster, like
the גמרא before about קרוב להחמיץ. karov lehachmitz. So there's one position
which is if you bake stuff with fruit juices, bake it right
away, fine, it's like, you know, you can make מצה, matzah. you
can make it non חמץ, chametz, but if you let it rise.
You can't use it for מצה matzah because of מצה עשירה. matzah
ashira. But if you baked it, you can eat it on פסח.
Pesach, But if you let it wait before baking it,
then even with fruit juices, we have to assume that it's at
least a quasi חמץ. chametz That's one position in the ראשונים. Rishonim
Another very dominant position in the ראשונים Rishonim. by תוספות Tosafot is
there's two types of scenario. Fruit juices with water added and fruit
juices without water added. Fruit juices without water added, it doesn't become
חמץ chametz. at all. And basically you could make dough with fruit
juices and let it sit out for an hour and go ahead
and make, you know, pastries with it and if there's no water
added, it doesn't become חמץ chametz at all. With water added does
become חמץ, chametz maybe even faster, maybe quasi חמץ, chametz. but all
of the problems are only with water added. Okay, so those are
the two positions in the ראשונים. Rishonim In the שולחן ערוך, Shulchan
Aruch, the שולחן ערוך Shulchan Aruch rules this second way. And the
שולחן ערוך Shulchan Aruch actually says, if you make stuff with just
fruit juice, with no water added, you don't have to, you know,
bake it or whatever, you can let it rise, the whole thing.
It's sort of like rice, you know, it's not a problem. In
the same way you can make stuff out of rice according to
the עיקר הלכה, ikkar halacha, you can make with flour and fruit
juices as long as you don't add water, and you don't have
to rush to bake it like מצה matzah, and so on. It's
not a problem, it will never become חמץ. chametz That's how the
שולחן ערוך Shulchan Aruch rules. The רמ״א, Rama, not surprisingly, the same
רמ״א Rama and the אשכנזים Ashkenazim who treat, have the whole קטניות
kitniyos thing with rice, say the מנהג minhag is to say that
fruit juices can become חמץ. chametz, To say אין מחמיצין ein machmitzin
means that they don't become, you're not חייב כרת, chayiv kares, but
it's quasi חמץ, chametz even without water added. The other approach I
said, that even without water, fruit juices aren't full חמץ chametz. but
they are quasi חמץ. Okay, and therefore the practice is even if
no water was used for אשכנזים, Ashkenazim, not to eat מצה matzah.
made with things made with fruit juice unless for the sake of
like צורך החולה. tzorech hacholeh. So actually if you buy now, you
know, מצות, matzahs you know, for, there are מצות matzahs, that are
כשר לפסח, kosher lepesach, egg מצות, matzahs without water added and on
the side it says to be used only for החולה hacholeh or
whatever. And קטנים ktanim and so on. Now the irony is that
this whole discussion is when you didn't bake it into מצה. matzah?
Can you use, right? If it doesn't become חמץ it means even
without baking it into מצה matzah. it's okay. So therefore in principle
if you actually baked it into מצה, matzah it should be no
stricter
than water. Okay, but nevertheless somehow the same way we go crazy
by קטניות, kitniyos, I'm allowed to eat plain flour if I made
sure that חמץ didn't come into touch or if I take a
grain kernel, right? I know water didn't come in touch with it.
I can eat that on פסח, Pesach? right? But you know what
I can't eat on פסח? Pesach Corn. No, plain corn. I can
eat wheat but I can't eat corn. So you have a similar
type of a thing that happens by here, that even though here
the idea is is that you should be able to eat it
if it was baked into מצה. matzah The whole question is can
you eat it without having baked it into מצה? matzah Somehow now
we don't even eat egg מצות matzahs even if they're baked into
מצה. matzah. Okay, so this is the principle that אין פירות מחמיצין.
ein peiros machmitzim. So to repeat, according to some that means that
it's without water, it never becomes חמץ. With water it's different, without
water it never becomes חמץ and you don't have to bake it
into מצה Matzah, and you can do whatever you want with it
as long as you don't add water. And according to the רמ״א,
Rama, he's מחמיר machmir that even without water it might become חמץ,
but except for חולה, choleh, but what that logically would mean is
that if you bake it quickly you're okay. But in practice it
means even when we bake egg מצות matzahs and we are strict
about it, even that we don't use except for a חולה. choleh.
One last point which is there's a discussion about eggs. Eggs aren't
discussed here. So some ראשונים think maybe eggs is more strict than
fruit juices because the dough gets a lot thicker when you use
eggs and maybe therefore it is מחמיץ machmitz than fruit juices, but
the general consensus is to treat eggs just like other fruit juices.
Yes, quickly.
My question is then according to these viewpoints of saying it's not
חמץ at all, yes, would you make a המוציא hamotzi on it?
No, you wouldn't, unless water was added, right? But according to but
once water's added then everybody agrees that it's some degree of חמץ.
Okay, so we've covered a lot of things. Right. I'd have to
check back to that. We've covered a lot of things. We've
covered the five grains and discussed oats and celiacs. We've discovered rice
and the idea of אין מחמיץ, ein machmitz, which doesn't mean ferment,
it means something else. And now fruit juices and discovered egg מצות
Matzot and אין מחמיצין. ein machmitzin. Now we continue with the more
technical issues about the משנה. Mishnah Let's see if we can get
closer to let's see if we can do this pretty quickly. יוצאין
בדמאי ובמעשר. Yotzin bidmai ubema'aser. You can use grain made from דמאי.
demai. דמאי. Demai. So דמאי, demai, הא לא חזי ליה, halo chazi
lei, you can't eat it. And if you can't eat it, presumably
we're going to see later that there's a פסוק pasuk that says
that you're not יוצא yotzei well whatever. Either it'll be a פסוק
posuk that'll say you're not יוצא yotzei. with מצה Matzah. that is
forbidden to be eaten or it might just be a more general
idea that רש״י says here a number of times which is מצוה
הבאה בעבירה. mitzvah habah be'aveirah. That if you if there's a transgression.
intertwined with your מצוה mitzvah of eating the מצה if you transgress
then that gets in the way of you being יוצא. yotzei. So
הלא חזי ליה halo chazi lei or again it just might be
a more generic point forgetting the עבירה aveira that you have to
be it has to be fit for eating and it's not considered
fit for eating. So it says ah you're not allowed to eat
something that's דמאי, demai, at least not rabbinically. So maybe rabbinically at
least you shouldn't be יוצא. yotzei גמרא says כיון דאי בעי מפקר
לנכסיה הוי עני וחזי ליה keivan d'ee bei mafker l'nechasei havei ani
v'chazi lei no, theoretically you could eat it. You could renounce ownership
of all your property and become a pauper and then you'd be
allowed to eat דמאי demai cause the rabbis were lenient since again
this was only a rabbinic issue. Biblically we could assume that the
תרומות ומעשרות terumos u'ma'asros were taken. Paupers are allowed to eat דמאי
demai and so you could in theory become a pauper. השתא נמי
חזי ליה hashta nami chazi lei so here too in theory it's
fit for you. דתנן d'tenan we taught in the משנה Mishnah מאכילין
את העניים דמאי ואת האכסניא דמאי ma'achilin es ha'aniyim demai v'es ha'achsanya
demai you can feed the paupers דמאי demai and אכסניא achsanya רש״י
says it means like troops that you have to quarter, even Jewish
troops, you can feed them דמאי demai ואמר רב הונא v'amar Rav
Huna תנא that we taught in a ברייתא Beraita בית שמאי אומרים
אין מאכילין את העניים דמאי ואין את האכסניא דמאי Beis Shammai omrim
ein ma'achilin es ha'aniyim demai v'ein es ha'achsanya demai בית שמאי Beis
Shammai says you're not allowed and בית הלל Beis Hillel says you
can and therefore since in theory you could eat it, it's not
considered uneatable. One way of understanding this also is where do you
ever have a type of a food that is considered forbidden food
מאכלות אסורות ma'achalos assuros that can be eaten by poor people that
we're lenient. That we ever say oh you know if you cook
chicken with milk that's rabbinically forbidden but poor people can eat it
right we would never say something like that. So that might be
the point of the גמרא. The fact that we allow poor people
to eat it shows that we don't treat
דמאי demai as forbidden food. We obligate you to take תרומות ומעשרות
terumos u'ma'asros again, we might say you can't eat it, but it's
not the same quality as forbidden food because some people are allowed
to eat it. And therefore because it's not that quality of forbidden
food you could be יוצא yotzei, with it for פסח for
מצה. מעשר ראשון שנטלה תרומתו ma'aser rishon shenitla terumato also מעשר ma'aser
that the תרומה terumah was taken from it. פשיטא pishita of course
once the מעשר ma'aser has the תרומה terumah the tenth of the
tenth taken from it, it's totally חולין. chulin. דכיון שנטלה תרומתו
חולין הוא d'keivan shenitla terumato chulin hu it's totally unsanctified grain, why
should there be an issue? לא צריכא lo tzricha you need it
שהקדימו בשבולין shehikdimo beshibolim that the לוי Levi sort of beat out
the כהן Kohen while the stuff was in the stalks ונטלו ממנו
תרומת מעשר v'natlu mimenu terumas ma'aser
yes the לוי Levi got basically he came to the owner before
the wheat had been harvested, he asked for his מעשר ma'aser upfront,
the guy gave him the מעשר ma'aser upfront without ever having taken
תרומה terumah from it. He gave him the מעשר ma'aser before the
כהן. Kohen. Then when the לוי Levi had his מעשר ma'aser he
took the second מעשר, ma'aser, the תרומת מעשר terumas ma'aser and that
he did give to the כהן. Kohen. ונטלה ממנו תרומת מעשר v'natla
mimenu terumas ma'aser he took the תרומת מעשר terumas ma'aser ולא נטלה
הימנו תרומה גדולה v'lo nutla heimenru terumah gedolah but the original תרומה
terumah was never taken from the grain. So you would think if
original תרומה terumah wasn't taken from the grain without all the things
having been taken it remains טבל. tevel. But no, there's an exception
this case it's okay וכדרבי אבהו u'che'Rabbi Abbahu like רבי אבהו Rabbi
Abbahu דאמר רבי אבהו אמר ריש לקיש d'amar Rabbi Abbahu amar Reish
Lakish
מעשר ראשון שהקדימו בשבולין ma'aser rishon shehikdimo beshibolim if the first tithe
the לוי Levi beat out the כהן Kohen and asked for his
tithe when it was still in the sheaves. I said stalks, I
meant sheaves. פטור מתרומה גדולה patur miterumah gedolah you don't have to
give תרומה גדולה. terumah gedolah. You can give him his מעשר ma'aser
and he has to give the מעשר ma'aser of the מעשר ma'aser
the תרומת מעשר. terumas ma'aser. But since he beat out the כהן
Kohen you don't have to give the תרומה גדולה terumah gedolah from
what was given to the לוי. Levi. Why? שנאמר shenemar והרמותם ממנו
תרומת השם מעשר מן המעשר vaharimotem mimenu terumat Hashem ma'aser min hama'aser
it says that the לוי Levi should take the תרומת מעשר terumas
ma'aser from their tithe from their מעשר ma'aser a tenth of a
tenth. מעשר מן המעשר אמרתי לך ma'aser min hama'aser amarti lach take
a tenth out of your tithe ולא תרומה גדולה ותרומת מעשר מן
המעשר v'lo terumah gedolah v'terumas ma'aser min hama'aser but you don't also
have to take תרומה גדולה terumah gedolah from your tithe. So if
you got your tithe without תרומה terumah being taken from it you
don't have to take תרומה terumah if you beat out the כהן
Kohen and jumped and before when the stuff was still in the
sheaves out in the field.
Now the בעל הבית ba'al habayit still
has to give תרומה terumah on the rest but he doesn't have
to give תרומה terumah on the מעשר ma'aser he gave you. אמר
ליה רב פפא לאביי amar lei Rav Papa l'Abaye רב פפא Rav
Papa said to אביי Abaye אלא מעתה ela me'ata if that's true
that he never has to give a tithe אפילו הקדימו בכרי afilu
hikdimo bikari even afterwards in the sheaves, even once it was piled
up like the grain was winnowed and threshed and it was made
into a big pile of grain, even there would you say that
he doesn't have to give תרומה terumah if he beat out the
כהן? Kohen?
ליפטר lipater let him be exempt. אמר ליה עליך אמר קרא amar
lei alecha amar kra in response to you the פסוק posuk says
מכל מתנתיכם תרימו את כל תרומת השם mikol matnoséichem tarimu es kol
terumas Hashem another פסוק posuk by תרומת מעשר terumas ma'aser says from
all of your gifts you shall give all of the תרומות. terumos.
So one פסוק posuk says to לויים Levi'im only give תרומת מעשר
terumas ma'aser the tenth of the tenth another פסוק Pasuk, says give
all of the תרומות terumos from your tithe. Sometimes you'll get your
tithe and you'll still have to give the תרומה גדולה. terumah gedolah.
So what's the difference? ומאי ראית u'mai ra'ita why did you distinguish
between whether it's in the sheaves or whether it's been winnowed and
threshed and in the pile? האי אדגן והאי לא אדגן hai idgan
v'hai lo idgan one is being considered grain and the other is
not grain. Meaning the basic principle is that until the grain has
been threshed and winnowed and put in a pile and the pile
smoothed over, which is called מירוח, miruach, until that
point it is not yet fully obligated in תרומות ומעשר. terumot u-ma’aser.
You can take תרומות ומעשר terumot u-ma’aser earlier, but it’s not fully
obligated. So here’s the point. If the לוי Levi comes to the
owner when it’s in the sheaves before it’s been fully processed, it’s
not yet obligated in תרומה. terumah. So if he got his מעשר
ma’aser then, he escapes ever having to give תרומה. terumah. But once
it’s been threshed and winnowed and processed and put in the pile
and whatnot and become obligated in תרומה, terumah, then if the לוי
Levi comes and gets his מעשר ma’aser first, he has to give
the תרומה terumah because the grain already became obligated. So the basic
point being this משנה Mishnah that said מעשר ma’aser is okay is
even in the special case where you got out of giving תרומה.
terumah. Let’s read a little bit more.
מעשר שני והקדש שנפדו. Ma’aser Sheni ve-Hekdesh she-nifdu. Also you can use
מעשר שני Ma’aser Sheni and הקדש Hekdesh that have been redeemed. פשיטא,
Pshita, obviously, once they’ve been redeemed they’re totally normal. הכא במאי עסקינן,
Hacha be-mai askinan, what are we talking about? שנתן את הקרן ולא
נתן את החומש, She-natan et ha-keren ve-lo natan et ha-chomesh, that when
you redeem them you have to add a fifth and you redeemed
them without adding a fifth. So it was somewhat problematic. וקמשמע לן
דאין חומש מעכב, Ve-ka-mashma lan de-ein chomesh me’akev, and it’s telling you
it doesn’t matter, as long as it was redeemed, even if it
wasn’t done with the extra fifth, it’s enough to remove the sanctity
and you can use it. והכהנים בחלה ובתרומה, Ve-ha-kohanim be-challah u-ve-terumah, כהנים
Kohanim can use חלה Challah and תרומה, terumah, because for them they’re
allowed to eat חלה Challah and תרומה. terumah. פשיטא, Pshita, that’s obvious.
No, מהו דתימא, Mahu de-teima, I might have thought, מצה שווה לכל
אדם בעינן, Matzah shaveh le-chol adam ba’inan, that maybe it has to
be מצה, maybe it has to be edible by everybody to be
considered מצה. קמשמע לן, Ka-mashma lan, מצות מצות ריבה, Matzot Matzot ribah,
it says מצות in the plural to tell you even if it’s
not edible by everyone, even stuff as long as it’s edible by
you that’s enough. So again,
I don’t know. So the principle is that the stuff has to
be edible even if it’s only edible by you, like the חלה
Challah and the stuff like here, like by the
מעשר ma’aser that didn't have the תרומה terumah taken but it was
okay or the הקדש hekdesh that was redeemed. These are cases where
it is מותר mutar to be eaten, but I might have thought
it was somewhat problematic and it’s telling me that it’s okay. Let’s
just, I know we’re a little bit over but we started late.
I’m going to just read a little bit more. If you have
to go, you have to go. So the משנה says, אבל לא
בטבל, Aval lo be-tevel, you can't eat טבל. Tevel. פשיטא, Pshita, that’s
also obvious, that can’t be eaten. So no, צריכה בטבל טבול מדרבנן,
Tzrichah be-tevel tavul mi-derabbanan, it’s Rabbinic טבל, Tevel, שזרעו בעציץ שאינו נקוב,
She-zara’o be-atzitz she-eino naku’v, which grew in a flowerpot without a hole.
So therefore it’s not considered biblically obligated, it’s not connected to the
ground, but it is Rabbinic and it’s worse than דמאי. Demai. Nobody’s
allowed to eat this and therefore even though it’s only Rabbinic you
do not fulfill your obligation, at least your Rabbinic though fulfill your
obligation. ולא במעשר ראשון שלא נטלה תרומתו, Ve-lo be-ma’aser rishon she-lo nitlah
terumato, not מעשר ראשון Ma’aser Rishon without תרומה terumah taken. פשיטא, Pshita,
obviously that’s טבל. Tevel. No, צריכה שהקדימו בכרי. Tzrichah she-hikdimo be-chari. No,
it’s the other side of the case we said before, that the
לוי Levi got his מעשר ma’aser but it was after the grain
had already been winnowed but he got it before the כהן. Kohen.
מהו דתימא כדאמר ליה רב פפא לאביי, Mahu de-teima ke-de-amar lei Rav
Pappa le-Abaye, maybe I would have thought like רב פפא Rav Pappa
to אביי, Abaye, that maybe even in that case you don't have
to give תרומה terumah because you beat out the כהן. Kohen. קמשמע
לן כדשני ליה, Ka-mashma lan ke-di-shani lei, so the משנה is telling
you no, in that case you do have to give תרומה terumah
because even though the לוי Levi beat out the כהן, Kohen, it
had already been made into a pile and therefore it had already
become obligated in תרומה. terumah. And the very last case we'll do
today, ולא במעשר שני והקדש שלא נפדו, Ve-lo be-ma’aser sheni ve-hekdesh she-lo
nifdu, not מעשר שני Ma’aser Sheni and הקדש Hekdesh that have not
been redeemed. פשיטא, Pshita, that’s also obvious, if they're not redeemed they
can't be eaten out of ירושלים, Yerushalayim, or can't be eaten at
all if it's הקדש. Hekdesh. לא לעולם דנפדו, Lo le-olam de-nifdu, no,
really it was redeemed. ומאי שלא נפדו, U-mai she-lo nifdu, what does
it mean it wasn't redeemed? שלא נפדו כהלכתן, She-lo nifdu ke-hilchatan, it
wasn't redeemed fully according to הלכה. מעשר שני שפדהו על גבי אסימון,
Ma’aser Sheni she-padahu al gabei asimon, מעשר שני Ma’aser Sheni was redeemed
on a coin that does not have an image on it, is
not like minted. רחמנא אמר וצרת הכסף, Rachmana amar ve-tzarta ha-kesaf, the
רחמנא Rachmana said וצרת הכסף, ve-tzarta ha-kesaf, you shall bind the money.
דבר שיש לו צורה, Davar she-yesh lo tzurah, you can only redeem
מעשר שני Ma’aser Sheni on a coin that has an image, that
has been minted. So if it was a non-minted coin, it was
just a piece of metal, it didn't work. והקדש, Ve-hekdesh, and about
הקדש, Hekdesh, שחילה על גבי קרקע, she-chillah al gabei karka, you redeemed
it but you redeemed it on land and you're not allowed to
redeem הקדש Hekdesh on land, it has to be on chattel. רחמנא
אמר ונתן הכסף וקם לו, Rachmana amar ve-natan ha-kesef ve-kam lo, the
רחמנא Rachmana says ונתן הכסף וקם לו, ve-natan ha-kesef ve-kam lo, you
should give the money and it'll be yours, actually that's not a
פסוק, but okay, and therefore the principle, therefore it was not a
good redemption. So the upshot of this is not bad, we finished
the whole דף Daf in like seven minutes, that side of it.
The upshot of this is that if the stuff can be eaten,
then you're יוצא, yotzei, even if it can only be eaten by
כהנים Kohanim and there's some cases where I might have thought it's
problematic, you didn't add the חומש, chomesh, you beat the כהן Kohen
out, but nevertheless it's okay. And if it can't be eaten, you're
not יוצא, even if it only can't be eaten מדרבנן, mi-derabbanan, like
the Rabbinic טבל, Tevel, or even cases that there was a technical
reason why it's still forbidden, like you tried to redeem it on
the wrong types of things. Nevertheless, if at the end of the
day it can't be eaten, then you are not יוצא מצה yotzei
Matzah and we will continue to discuss why you're not יוצא מצה
yotzei Matzah if it can't be
eaten. If it's forbidden to be eaten, we'll discuss that then.
The משנה *Mishnah* says these are the things with which a person
is יוצא *yotze* their obligation on פסח *Pesach*: with חטים *chitim*, with
שעורים *se'orim*, with כוסמין *kusmin*, with שיבולת שועל *shibolet shual*, and with
שיפון *shiffon*. These are the חמשת מיני דגן *chameshet minei dagan*. The
גמרא *Gemara* explains that only things that can become חמץ *chametz* are
valid for מצה *matzah*. This is learned from a היקש *hekesh* in
the פסוק *pasuk* between מצה *matzah* and חמץ *chametz*. Therefore, אורז *orez*
and דוחן *dochan* are excluded because they don't reach the state of
חימוץ *chimutz*, but rather סירחון *sirachon*. רבי יוחנן בן נורי *Rabbi Yochanan
ben Nuri* says אורז *orez* is a species of דגן *dagan*, but
the חכמים *Chachamim* say it is not. We only use these species
to be יוצא *yotze* the מצוה *mitzvah* of מצה *matzah*.